<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true mariner, and his pixis nautica: or, the expert navigator, with his metaphorical and hieroglyphical ship, described and platformed; to demonstrate the way to paradise. / Written by Tho. Elslyot, Ar. Ar. Conq. To the glory of God, and advancement of Christ's kingdom; for the good of the present English commonwealth and armies, and for the good of all future representatives in resemblance of former good Parliaments; and also, for the advancement of navigation thorowout the whole world.</title>
            <author>Elsliot, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84397</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865745</idno>
  <idno type="VID">117996</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248498360</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E656_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206626</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865745</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99865745e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84397)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 101:E656[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true mariner, and his pixis nautica: or, the expert navigator, with his metaphorical and hieroglyphical ship, described and platformed; to demonstrate the way to paradise. / Written by Tho. Elslyot, Ar. Ar. Conq. To the glory of God, and advancement of Christ's kingdom; for the good of the present English commonwealth and armies, and for the good of all future representatives in resemblance of former good Parliaments; and also, for the advancement of navigation thorowout the whole world.</title>
                  <author>Elsliot, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 32, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 18 1651"; also the last number of the imprint date has been marked through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117996:1"/>
            <p>The true Mariner, AND HIS <hi>PIXIS NAƲTICA:</hi> OR, The Expert NAVIGATOR, WITH HIS Metaphorical and Hieroglyphical SHIP, Described and Platformed; to demonstrate the way to PARADISE.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Tho. Elslyot,</hi> Ar. Ar. Conq.</p>
            <p>To the glory of God, and advancement of Christ's kingdom; for the good of the present <hi>English</hi> Commonwealth and Armies, and for the good of all future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentatives in resemblance of former good Parliaments; AND ALSO, For the advancement of NAVIGATION thorowout the whole world.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London,</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117996:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:117996:2"/>
            <head>To his Excellency the Lord General <hi>OLIVER CROMWEL,</hi> Esq; Captain General of all the English Forces now or late under the Command of the Parliament of the English Nation, and Lord Governor of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble General,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eriously considering with my self, what great pains the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> hath for these many yeers taken in their Diurnal and Nocturnal lucubrations, and constant sitting in the Parliament-House in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> now for the space of these full <hi>11</hi> yeers last past; to the great neglect of their Country-occasions, their wives and families, and much impoverishing divers worthy members in that honorable Assembly, and all under pretence of a perfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, both in Church and Commonwealth, if an honest man may believe them; and it may be divers of them, in the infancy of this Parliament and Commonwealth, had cordially intended the same; but how the devil hath cast his club over their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, according to the old English Proverb, and the great <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> blasted all the spiritual hopes of so great a blessing, of their good intents, and his kindness and mercy, to and upon this Nation and Commonwealth, let the world judge, by the evils past, and daily still threatned; therefore certainly it is to be feared that there are some <hi>Achans</hi> in the Camp, (which caused <hi>Joshua</hi> to turn his back of the men of <hi>Ai</hi>) which must be sought out;
<pb facs="tcp:117996:3"/> for they be troublers of <hi>Israel,</hi> and of a truth have taken the silver, and wedge of gold, and the rich Babylonish garment, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in the <hi>7</hi> of <hi>Joshua,</hi> and the <hi>21 verse;</hi> which hath so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased the Lord, that he turneth his back of his own people, in this good work of reformation. And therefore, my Lord, not impertinently, but very properly and prophetically was it spoken of that gentleman in the house of Commons, much about the time when the plenipotentiary Commission was given unto the late General the Lord <hi>Fairefax,</hi> then Sir <hi>Thomas Fairefax,</hi> about the time of the new modellizing of the Armies now under the Command of your Excellency; who (openly speaking of the late tyrant and murderer, justly destroyed by a providential hand of supernatural power) said, that there was a <hi>Jonas</hi> in the ship of this Commonwealth and English Nation, that resisted the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate commands of the Lord of Hosts, and King Jesus his Son, your Lordships and Armies, and this present Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths great Captain General, and he that hath given your Lordship all your recent victories against the enemies of this present Commonwealth. And so long as <hi>Jonas</hi> was in the ship uncast overboard, in vaine was it for the Mariners to labor or velificate against the seas, windes, and stormes which the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God had raised against the ship wherein <hi>Jonas</hi> was; (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the first Chapter of <hi>Jonahs</hi> prophesie, unto the <hi>15 vers.</hi>) untill <hi>Jonas</hi> was cast overboard, and then the storme ceased. But, my Lord I am affraid there be abundance of <hi>Jonases</hi> in the ship of this present Commonwealth, that if they do not very speedily repent them, and that within few dayes after they shall have notice of this Metaphorical ship, which is to be built by your Lordship, and the Armies, and Commonwealth, with all speed, if you intend to assist King Jesus in deposing of all the kings of the earth, and think your self fit to be a weddinger at the marriage of the Lamb of righteousness, which is very live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly laid down and expressed, in the <hi>19</hi> of the <hi>Revel.</hi> of Saint <hi>John,</hi> of which the penman hereof is confident your Lordship is very well versed in.</p>
            <p>And, my Lord, I let your Lordship further know, that if your Lordship will be a means to save all the blood which will be shed
<pb facs="tcp:117996:3"/> upon mankind by the ensuing plague (which if this ship be not built and sent to sea) will inevitably follow this Summer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the males of the English Nation, foreshowen by the great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Eclipse, happening to be upon the <hi>29</hi> day of <hi>March</hi> ensuing; when of a truth parcel of mother <hi>Shiptons</hi> prophesie will come to pass) and save your honors life into the bargain, that you forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with call a Council of the most faithful and most Christian Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, friends, and ministers of Jesus Christ, to consult with your Excellency about the meaning of this Metaphorical and Hieroglyphical forme of a ship platformed unto your Lordships hand; and out of them to Elect you a person so qualified, as is in the same described, for the speedy velification thereof, for the purposes in her remonstrances expressed, in such manner and form, and with such velocity as is therein described, to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that she return before the <hi>14</hi> of <hi>May</hi> next; for in case she do not, wo be to the man-kind in <hi>England:</hi> and as I am a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Jesus Christ, and of this present Commonwealth, I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure your Lordship, foreseeing these great evils to come, out of my duty to the Commonwealth, and the love to my own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen, and honor to your Lordship, and soldiery, who hath with Gods blessing freed me from the tyranny of a temporal Prince, by often adventuring of your blood in the field, for the good of the lambs of this present Commonwealth, like as my blessed Saviour by shedding of his innocent blood, for the redemption of my soul from my scarlet sins committed in my youth, and therein hath not only made me free in spirit from the curse of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, due to such miserable sinners as I do confess my self to be; but also hath freed me from the bondage of Satan: therefore about the <hi>16</hi> of <hi>Novem.</hi> last, I did seriously resolve to abstaine from bread or food for six whole months, to make me to humble my self to the living God, the Father of all spirits; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and constantly beseeching of him, for the Lord Jesus Christ his sake, to avert his heavy judgements hovering and pendent over the head of this Nation, pointed at shrewdly by the Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers this yeer; being in that confidence that King <hi>David</hi> was in (expressed in the second book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> at the <hi>21 vers.</hi> of the <hi>7 Chap.</hi>) who fasted all the while the child was alive, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suming
<pb facs="tcp:117996:4"/> of the goodness of God; for, said he (at the <hi>21</hi> verse▪ the said Chapter) <hi>Who can tell whether God will be gratious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that the childe may live?</hi> And without doubt, if <hi>David</hi> had humbled himself sooner, before the living God had pronounced the letter of Mort against the infant by the prophet <hi>Nathan,</hi> I am confident God would have been gracious unto him, and the childe had lived: and so I am confident also that if the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans directions be timely observed about the ship herewith first dedicated unto your Excellency and your Armies, and then to the Commonwealth, the judgement determined, shall be sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spended, as in <hi>Ahabs</hi> case, recorded in the <hi>21 Chap.</hi> and last <hi>ver.</hi> in the first book of <hi>Kings,</hi> upon <hi>Ahabs</hi> half-way-humiliation. But what should I trouble your Lordship with examples, when your Lordship may very well be my School-master! But, my Lord, it is possible your Lordship may shew these presents unto some scoffing <hi>Ishmaels,</hi> or <hi>Davids</hi> fools; but they be well described in the <hi>53 Psalm, vers. 1.</hi> Take heed you do not believe them; for their ways be corrupt, and will do what they can to ensnare your just soul, which I am confident stands as yet right in the presence of my King, your Generalissimo, and for ever will be confirmed, if your heart stands right with the wayes of the Lord, and continues but as perfect in Garison, as it is in Field against your enemies; and so, my Lord, I rest;</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given from my quarters neer the <hi>Black</hi>-dogg at <hi>Newgate,</hi>
                  <date>this <hi>7.</hi> of <hi>March 1651.</hi> being four moneths of my voluntary fast of the six months e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapsed.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I Your Most humble servant and member of Jesus Christ, and of this Commonwealth, Tho. Elslyot</hi> Ar. Ar. Conq.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117996:4"/>
            <head>To all Officers of Military Discipline and all the rest of the soldiery, being Saints of the presen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> English Armies in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> under the Command of <hi>OLIVER CROMWEL,</hi> Esq; Captain General of all the English Forces in either of the two Nations; as also to those in <hi>Ireland,</hi> now under his Excellencies command there as Lord Governor of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as, my brethren and fellow-soldiers, our blessed Saviour Jesus Christ, the only begotten Son of God the Father, by the determinate will of God, being before the foundations of the world were laid, in fulness of time left the bosome of his heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, and took our nature upon him, to be born into this miser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able world, and here to live a poor, wretched, and miserable life, to the end that he might be crucified for the redemption of mankind, to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his heavenly Fathers Divine Justice and wrath for the sins of the miserable lost sons of our parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer death, sin, and hell, by his death and passion; by means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and faith in him, we be not only freed from the curse of God due to sinners, but also delivered out of the bondage of Satan, that old enemy of mankind: So you likewise, dearly beloved friends, not only have freed my self, but the three Nations, by Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, your noble General and your good endeavors, with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding
<pb facs="tcp:117996:5"/> of your blood, lives and fortunes, from the bondage of tyrannical Kings the restoring of my self and the English Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to their prestine freedoms and priviledges of true English men, and delivering of us from the bonage of the <hi>Norman</hi> yoak; so that now we be a free people indeed, neither is there any Nation in the world like unto the English Nation, who be both Christians, and a wise and ingenious people; wherefore I have writ this Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorical and Hieroglyphical ship, in thankfulness unto you, dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the noble General in the first place to your selves in the next, and to every free-born English man, who desires to serve the Lord of Hosts in spirit and truth, and King Jesus your heavenly Captaine General, who hath owned you and your noble General in the day of battel, and given unto you so many notable victories over your and the Commonwealths enemies, To teach and instruct you how to keep these victories the living God hath given to you, by fetching of justice and mercy into this Nation again, and establishing them here for the age of <hi>Methusalah;</hi> and do advise you speedily to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition his Excellency for that purpose hereafter remonstrated, which will free you from the plague and other imminent dangers, which the Solar Eclipse this <hi>March</hi> doth threaten this Nation withall, but especially mankinde; (for I fear many of you will not live to enjoy the fruits of your labors) and that you be sure to learn to do unto every man as you would be done unto. And if you do, I who have vowed to eat no bread for six moneths for your sakes, shall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to perform my promise unto you, and to cloath you all in scarlet, and gaine all your ariears, according to my ingagement: and in case you do not, nevertheless I have out of a good conscience done my duty to God Almighty, and to you; and so I rest</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given from my quarters</hi>
                  <date>this 7 <hi>day of</hi> March 1651 <hi>and in the sixteenth week of my abstinence from food for your sakes, and the glory of Gods mercy in Christ.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your faithful servant to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and a member of Jesus Christ and of this present Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth <hi>Tho Elslyot Ar. Ar. Conq.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117996:5"/>
            <head>To all and every free-born person of this English Nation and Commonwealth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas (my brethren) I am very sinsible of the great taxes and burthens that do at present lye upon you, and all the whole Commonwealth, occasioned partly by divers of your stubbornesses to the honorable Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> who either <hi>Jew</hi>-like, or <hi>Herodian</hi>-like, desired ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have a temporal King, called <hi>Cesar</hi> in that age, and <hi>Charls Stuart</hi> in this age, then to have their King <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> the only Son of God, who hath shed his innocent blood for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem your souls from eternal damnation, albeit it was expresly against the second Petition of the Lords prayer, which you stand so much for; and whereas his Excellency and the present English Armies, I am confident, be right sorry to see you so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day taxed and rated, Sequestred or plundered, if you would live peaceably and quietly in the present Commonwealth, and joyn together, and repaire to his Excellency or his Counsel of war, to Petition his Excellencie and armies to be a means to help to take off your taxes and burthens, upon condition you will joyn with them for the fitting and setting out of the ship describ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ensuing remonstrance, to bring home Justice and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy again into this land; for after they be seated in their proper places in this Commonwealth, there will be little or no use for
<pb facs="tcp:117996:6"/> further taxes or burthens in this Commonwealth; for of a truth then will the Lamb and Lion couch and lie down together, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ancient prediction of the Prophet <hi>Esay.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that Gods Judgements may be turned from this Nation, and your selves in particular, threatned this month, by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usual Solar Eclipse happening the <hi>29</hi> of <hi>March 1652,</hi> and other eminent dangers besides, if you follow this seasonable advice, your taxes vnd burthens shall be taken off, and so I rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Fellow-friend and servant, and member of Jesus Christ, and of this Present Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth. Tho. Elslyot</hi> Ar. Ar. Conq.</signed>
               <dateline>Given from my quarters <date>this <hi>7.</hi> day of <hi>March 1651.</hi> in the <hi>16</hi> week of my abstinance from food, for yours and the soldieries sakes, and the glory of Gods mercy in Christ.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117996:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The true REMONSTRANCE</hi> of the Metaphorical and Hieroglyphical new platformed Ship of <hi>Thomas Elslyot</hi> Esq; and member of Iesus Christ, and member of the English Commonwealth, and a free-born person of the English Nation, and Esquire at Arms, and Conqueror of the Gentleman of the Long Robe, (now or late Satan of this present Commonwealth) by Gods providence, his own innocency and sufferings, and by the justice of the honorable Lord Chief Iustice <hi>Rolle,</hi> and the rest of the Reverend Iudges of the Upper Bench in <hi>Westminster,</hi> before the Keepers of the Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> by authority of Parliament, the last <hi>Michaelmas</hi>-Term; presented to his Excellency and the Saints of the English Armies, and to every free-born English-man who loves Justice and Mercy.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow that onely one Almighty and Invisible God, the sole Lord and Creator of the heavens and earth, being Eternal, yea Eternity it self, Did content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in the three persons of the holy Trinity, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Son, and holy Ghost, revealed to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures reasonable since the beginning of this present world, or what he was doing before the foundations of the world were laid <hi>(non consiat)</hi> by his revealed Word, unto his creature Man: and therefore all the ancient Metaphysicks, Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles, Fathers of the Church, and Philosophers, have been silent, as holding it a great presumption, and an absurd scrutamen and investi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117996:7"/> for the creatures to pry or too curiously to enquire into the secrets of their Creator, having no warrant or ground thereof, out of the holy Writ, contained in the two books of the holy Bible (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Old and New Testaments.) And the courteous Reader, whosoever he be, must not expect from the Penman hereof, any such matter. Nevertheless, the Panman hereof doth first agree the holy Trinity with all the ancient Fathers, and doth much approve of the truth and antiquity of the Works of <hi>Mercurius Trismegistus,</hi> who (the Penman hereof doth believe) did live in the time of <hi>Serug, Abraham</hi>'s great grandfather, and was a King, a Priest, and a Prophet; who be onely truely written in the University of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and in the Penman's possession, that ever he could hear of, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where else in this Nation. And the Penman hereof doth also agree the Hierarchy of Angels expressed opinionatively by <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Johannes Paulus Palenterius,</hi> and the rest of the School-men and ancient Fathers: and is of opinion, that as all the nine orders of good Angels be but <hi>ministring spirits for the heirs of salvation,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> well testifies; yet he believes that no more but three of the Orders do administer betwixt heaven and earth, and that the other six Orders do day and night administer in the <hi>Coelum Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poereum,</hi> in the presence of the holy Trinity, for their Makers divine Worship, for the purposes aforesaid.</p>
            <p>But leaving those holy spirits to their ready, subtil, and nimble performance of the will and commands of their great Creator, and my Maker invisible, the Penman hereof will briefly descend to Man, as being a man himself; and in brief declare unto the world his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the duty of every Christian man (that expects to be saved by the sole merits of Jesus Christ, through the mercy of God the Father, and sanctification of the holy Ghost, when Christ shall judge the world in flaming fire;) which, in a word, is no more, but to serve the ever-living God as a Spirit of Omnipotencie, in spirit and truth, and in simplicity and truth of the inward man; and not hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically, and with outward Forms and Will-worship (as this Age doth too manifestly evidence) the sad effects whereof, and for want of neighbourly love to our fellow-creatures, in doing to every man as we desire they should do unto us, have pulled most deserved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon these Nations those heavie Judgements which these late yeers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117996:7"/> have produced, to the glory of God's Justice; whereas these Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might easily have escaped them, if they would but have known for what cause the righteous Judge of heaven and earth had made the world, and would have walked more after the Spirit, and less af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the flesh: for albeit Man consisteth of both, yet the Spirit being the nobler part, ought to be preferred before the flesh the baser.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Penman hereof doth first remonstrate unto the world, That (the wise <hi>Opifex rerum</hi>) the great JEHOVAH, the Creator of heaven and earth, so declared by <hi>Moses</hi> to the children of <hi>Israel,</hi> God's own peculiar people in that Age, which for ever be blessed and hallowed (being incomprehensible to his creature Man) Hath, by his holy Word, and miraculous works, expressed himself by five divine Attributes to his creature; as namely, by his Power, his Wisdom, his Truth, his Justice, and his Mercy, which was to shew to Men and Angels how the world was made, for the expression of the two last of the five divine Attributes of the ever-living God (Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and Mercy) which be totally fled out of the English Horizon, or at least are so obscured and eclipsed from the eyes of the free-born persons of the English Nation, that truely of late yeers they have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther been under a cloud, or else they have hid themselves in some den or cave in the bowels of the earth, not visible to any honest or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian man; or else they have taken shipping at some Port of this Nation (unknown as yet to the Penman hereof;) and having stoln aboard in some invisible Bottom, they have left and departed from <hi>Brute</hi>'s shore, now possest by the anciently-free-born people English men, and have sailed to the <hi>terra incognita,</hi> or else keep their resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>super altum maris,</hi> in old Law-French called <hi>Sur le hault del mere,</hi> in English, Upon the heighth of the Ocean: or else ever since Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi>'s time they be couched beyond the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Line in the Antipodes; and likely made that Voyage to Sea with him, &amp; taught him how to pass thorow the <hi>Magellanical</hi> Straights: but if they did of a truth, the Penman hereof is most confident they never as yet came back again.</p>
            <p>Therefore the Penman hereof, for the future good of this present infant-Commonwealth of three yeers old, the late new-born babe called the English Commonwealth, now in the vegetation thereof; and to the end that first it may be well nursed, and in its youth it may be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117996:8"/> vertuously brought up and educated in all the vertues and learning, divine and moral, and feats of armes, untill it grow to the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a perfect man (for of a truth it must be a very great Warrior and Conqueror, and shall subdue all the Nations of the earth, and Regions under the Sun, and bear rule over them, under King Jesus, untill the second coming of Christ, and shall live <hi>Methusalahs</hi> age) doth advise the English Nation, first to build a ship, consist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of timber and iron-work, metaphorically signifying of the two natures; spiritual and temporal, in resemblance of the two natures of the true King Christ the head thereof; to go to sea, and search, try, explore, and finde out, if possible, in all or any of the Regions under the Sun, where those two Divine attributes of the ever-living God, Justice and Mercy, be resident, be hid, or have obscured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves so long from the English Horizon; and having found them, to bring them back againe into this Nation and Commonwealth, to attend the marriage of the Lamb of righteousness, Christ the head of the same.</p>
            <p>But here is all the doubt, that they being found, will not come back without a new national engagement, taken solemnly by this Commonwealth, and that in the presence of Divine Majesty, that they may be admitted to their pristine jurisdiction; that is to say, that they being the principal attendants of King Jesus, the head of the English Commonwealth, may be used by all free-born English men in the same, and civilly steer all the actions, thoughts, words and deeds of the people thereof, from the highest to the lowest.</p>
            <p>But since without them there will be no happiness nor amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things, nor yet freedome from the present evils at this day seated and raigning in the same Commonwealth; the penman here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of could well advise, that this engagement be presently made, and that this ship be forthwith built and set to sea, that within three, four, five, or six moneths at farthest, it may saile over all the inhabited world, and finde, and bring with her those divine Attributes of Justice and Mercy back againe, with all speed into this Nation, to exercise their several divine qualities of justice and mercy with all speed in this Commonwealth, for fear that when the Prince of peace and righteousness should come riding hither upon his white
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117996:8"/> horse spoken of in the 6 Chapter and 2 verse, and in the 19 Chap. of the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Saint <hi>John,</hi> on purpose to marry this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in mercy, righteousness, truth and justice, to himself; if he do not miss or but finde the two divine attributes wanting, which be his attendants, and the wedding-garment of his heavenly Father: for of a truth if he do, it is to be feared that he will deal with it as he did with the man in the Gospel of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> witnessed to all eternity by the Evangelist, in the two and twentieth Chapter, and the 13 verse, that had not on him the wedding garment of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, the two divine attributes aforesaid, of Justice and Mercy.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Penman hereof doth first advise, that an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and prudent Master-Ship-Carpenter be sought out, who is wel skilled in Navitectury, Architectury, and Carination, and be sure that his materials of timber be well seasoned, sound, valid, and no wayes putrid, and his Iron-work perfectly good and well wrought, and tempered with the <hi>Vulcans</hi> hammer; and one that can perfectly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and well form and fabricate the bottom of this vessel, first in timber-work, making the keel thereof (if she be 550 tuns burthen) as sharp, mince, and tenuous as the edge of a sword, to lay half as deep in the water (when she is lanched) equally as her proportion of water she draws in sayling; to percute and glide sharply, nimbly, and eagerly through the Merdres of the liquidity of the watry ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, fish-like, or <hi>more piscino;</hi> and then with thin plates of Iron or Steel to cover the keel of her, which must be very well pitched and oyled, mixt with <hi>Saltprenellal</hi> powder, which hath been nine times boyled off the original liquor, before the <hi>Saltpremella,</hi> vulgarly called <hi>Sampernella,</hi> a degree above Salt-nitre, be calcined, ustrinat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or beaten to powder; which will ever guard the keel upon the ships sayling, or lying at Anchor, from any corruption, or furring: and then to see in order to her staunchness, tidiness, unleakiness, that she be well and surely colcked.</p>
            <p>This done in order to the foundation, the rest of her structure will easily follow; (for she will be quickly decked masted &amp; rigged) only that she may be velociously and nimbly navigated, velificated, and sailed, for the purpose aforesaid, besides the usual maritimal Masts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Sayls now adaies used, it were necessary, that besides (her main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117996:9"/> her fore-mast pole-sprit before, and meesning-mast behind) she had four pole-sprits armes, or maine-yards extraordinary, two fore and af the ship, for clothing of her, when she comes into the deeps beyond Saint <hi>Georges</hi> Channel, beyond the lands end of <hi>England,</hi> that may be used upon the <hi>Oceanus Magnus,</hi> but will not be so useful in the narrow seas, or neer any maine continent, in regard her Velificators and Navigators (upon accidental stormes, or shallow waters) cannot so easily command her, if she be clothed with so many sailes; and if that her wings be too long for her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, she is subject (Hawk-like) to precipitate, which will be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the sailers, and her passengers, if many be.</p>
            <p>And if the said ship be thus fitted with Cables, Anchors, Skiff, Long-boats, proper tackle, together with a convenient Rudder, and Helme in her Steeridge, and a proper Bidickle for two Compasses; Then the next thing in order to this long voyage and velocious passage, will be, to gaine an expert Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagator, well versed and experienced first in the seamans Compass, or Mariners Card, called <hi>Pixis Nautica,</hi> and in all things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to <hi>Pilatation,</hi> Navigation, and velification; and also such a person as is well skilled in the several Arts and Sciences of Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, Cosmograpy; Geometry, but especially in Logick, Philosophy, Arithemitick, and that is a perfect Mathematician, well grounded, read, and experienced in the Terrestrial and Celestial Globes, and is not ignorant in the use and experiment of the Cross-staff, Jacobs-staff, and sometimes heaving of the Mariners Log, and knows truely how to take an observation upon the Meridian Horoscope, by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Judgment of the raising or declining of the two Poles, Girdles, or <hi>Zones</hi> of the Celestial world, bounded by the two tropicks of <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Capricorn;</hi> and that knows certainly his latitude, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitude, altitude, and profundity, upon the elevation or loring of his degrees, passing to, from, or under the Equinoctial Line. And first of all, it will be necessary that this expert Navigator of this ship, thus built and fitted for the intended voyage, so speedily (with Gods assistance) to be set out by the Saints of the Armies of the English Commonwealth, and free-born persons of the same, be a member of Jesus Christ, well skilled in all the several liberal Sciences, and also a good Cosmographer, and very well versed in the first Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117996:9"/> of <hi>Genesis,</hi> written by <hi>Moses</hi> upon the creation of the world, and have the spirit of the wisdome of King Jesus, perfectly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, construe, and understand the meaning of the Holy Ghost, at and in the ninth verse of the said first Chapter, revealed in the book of God to miserable man many hundred years after his fall and the universal deluge, to the end he may know what was truly <hi>(ab origine)</hi> sea, and what dry land, and how to distinguish betwixt the <hi>Oceanus Magnus,</hi> and narrow seas, indraughts of seas or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, armes of seas, bayes, gulphes, ingurgitations, dead seas, and the red-sea, great stagnes, or standing pools or ponds, lakes, viva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, rivers navigable and unnavigable, rivulets, brooks, springs, and all living or running waters through the veins and pores of the earth, whatsoever were upon the original frame of the world, and since have been contingent upon the general deluge of the world, and since by several excursions, violent irruptions, springs, tides, and sea-gainings, and gettings of water upon the land, by several ebbings and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the sea after her first creation, and bounding thereof by the living God, since the fall of man, and since the general deluge of the world, expressed by <hi>Moses</hi> in the seventh Chapter of <hi>Genesis:</hi> and to be sure he be well able to expound the 11 verse of the said Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; alwayes remembring from the penman hereof, that there was no flowing or ebbing of seas, before the fall of man; and that the earth was cursed for his sake, witness the third Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and the 17, 18, 19 verses; albeit the gentle reader may see the earth was cursed, yet the sea was not, but her bounds first set her by the living God, were not broken, nor the fountaines of the great deeps broken up, nor the windows of heaven opened, untill the 600 yeer of <hi>Noahs</hi> life, in the second moneth, the 17 day of the moneth, witnessed by <hi>Moses</hi> in the aforesaid seventh Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and the 11 verse; neither doth the penman hereof believe that there was any ebbing or flowing untill then: neither needed there any; for the earth was in its creation more noble then the seas or waters, for that the bodily part of man, the Lord thereof, was formed out of earth, as appears by the second of <hi>Genesis</hi> and 7 verse: yet the <hi>Microcosme</hi> of mans body, which is his flesh, blood, and bone, and every several Muscle, Veine, Nerve, Artery, and Ligament of mans body, be composed and intermixed with the four elements of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117996:10"/> earth and water, fire and air, vivificated and quickned by the Spirit of God: the two first, in resemblance of the earth, whereof his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is made; and the two last in resemblance of the Spirit of the great JEHOVAH, inspired into man when man became a living soul, also witnessed and fully proved by the last-recited Text; and man being made Lord of the whole world, as appears by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> in the 8 Psalm, and in the first Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing created after God's own image, and having dominion given unto him of all God's creatures, both by and in the land and sea, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30 verses of the same first Chapter of <hi>Genesis.</hi> And therefore this is sufficient to convince any Christian man, that is not an atheist and an heathen, That there was no ebbing or flowing of Seas, until after the Fall of man; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would there ever have been any until this time, had man not sinned against his Creator, but continued in the state of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie.</p>
            <p>And as the said Navigator must thus be expert in the Seas, so al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so (if he be a real Cosmographer) he must be very skilful in the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Regions, Kingdoms, Nations, and People, inhabitants in all and every, or any part or place of the four parts of the world, described by the names of <hi>Europe, Asia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> being one onely entire dry land and continent, as appears by the 9 and 10 verses of the first Chapter of <hi>Genesis:</hi> albeit even in Paradise it self, or that <hi>Edenical</hi> garden of pleasure wherein man was placed; (then seated in <hi>Asia major,</hi> being in the East-parts of the world) there were several great Rivers, witness <hi>Moses</hi> in the second Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> some of them known by their names at this day; and in <hi>Moses</hi>'s time (albeit much corrupted by the Deluge) the name of the first being <hi>Pison,</hi> which is that <hi>Ganges</hi> now in the East-Indies, which compassed in those days the land of <hi>Havilah,</hi> whence the Penman hereof doth believe <hi>Solomon</hi> sent his ships from <hi>Ezion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geber</hi> and <hi>Eloth,</hi> at the side of the Red-sea, for his gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> witnessed in the 7 Chapter of the second book of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> at the 17 and 18 verses, and in sundry other places of holy Writ. And the name of the second River was <hi>Gihon,</hi> which some have suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be the river <hi>Nilus,</hi> which descends from <hi>Prester</hi>- (alias <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter) John</hi>'s Country, called the <hi>Lunae montes;</hi> but the Penman
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117996:10"/> hereof rather believes it to be the great River which runs thorow all <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> and falls into the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea on this side the <hi>Cape de bono speranzo,</hi> not far from the indraught to <hi>Prester John</hi>'s Country. And the third was <hi>Hiddikel,</hi> that which runs toward the East of <hi>Africa,</hi> upon which the <hi>Babel</hi> and other Cities spoken of in the 10 Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and the 8, 9 and 10 verses thereof, were founded by <hi>Nimrod</hi> the first Tyrant in the world. And the name of the fourth was <hi>Euphrates,</hi> that famous River still known by that name in <hi>Asia,</hi> and so often mentioned in all parts of holy Writ.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Penman hereof being fully assured that the first earthly Paradise or Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> described by <hi>Moses</hi> in the said second Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> was before the Deluge placed in <hi>Asia major</hi> (now so called) being that part of the world Eastward, where the living God placed the man whom he had made and formed out of the dust of the earth; the true description whereof, the Penman hereof did think fit to remonstrate to the world, to the end that if the intended Voyage aforesaid be forthwith undertaken by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigator aforesaid, and should happen to miss of his purpose in the Antipodes, and not to finde the Lord Justice and Lady Mercy, the two divine Attributes aforesaid, That then that he may not lose his Voyage, but to be sure to make a quick and safe return, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and honour of the English Nation, and to his own fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happiness in this present infant-Commonwealth, it will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary onely for him, after he hath loosed from his Port, and after he hath left the Lands-end of <hi>England,</hi> and made the height of the <hi>Azores</hi> Islands, which be thought to be the centre of the Ocean, and middle of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi>-Seas, and are called <hi>Michael Flores, Corves Westerly, Mederas, Terceras, Piqquo Phiole,</hi> and S. <hi>Georges,</hi> more South and by East, lying in the bowels of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi>-Sea, or <hi>Oceanus magnus,</hi> and being no dry land appointed by God in the Creation, that can be said to be appearing in the vegetable earth, spoken of by <hi>Moses,</hi> in the 9 and 10 verses of the first Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> but cast up by violent and acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal subterraneous fires proceeding out of the earth, occasioned by too much sulphurous and bituminous matter in the bottom of the Seas or depths in that place, which the Navigator must leave in his Start-board-hand,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117996:11"/> and keep his course directly according to his Compass, or <hi>Pixis Nautica,</hi> South South-east, and appoint more Southerly, until he come with the height of the <hi>Canary</hi>-Islands, likewise cast up long since the Creation by subterraneous fires, like as the <hi>Azores</hi> Islands were. And from thence (the <hi>Canary</hi>-Islands being left also on the Startboard-hand) the next work in point of Navigation is, to consider that now (to keep their intended course for the Antipodes) they must think upon the elevation of the height of his degree to the Meridian Horoscope, to pass under the Equinoctial Line, and to be well advised that his Saylors that be men of full bodies and san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine complexions, do take heed to keep a spare and wary diet, for fear of the Epidemical disease called the <hi>Calenture,</hi> which is incident to all humane bodies born under the Tropick of <hi>Cancer;</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to leave <hi>Cuba</hi> three degrees on the Start-board-hand to the West; and upon the taking or hitting of the Straights of <hi>Magel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanica,</hi> perfectly to be sure to keep his course well to the South and by West, betwixt the <hi>terra incognita,</hi> and the <hi>terra Della fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> and the Islands of <hi>Cacofogo,</hi> likewise vomited out of the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the earth, from the depths of the Seas in the Southern decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from the Equinoctial Line: and having passed those Islands, it will behove the aforesaid Navigator to direct his course South and by West, and appoint more westerly, until he have acquired the Longitude and Profundity of the West-<hi>Indies,</hi> which with much care and diligence will bring him along with Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> and Sir <hi>Martin Forbisher,</hi> unto the mouth of the Straights of <hi>Magel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanica,</hi> and there will be little or no use of the four additional Pole-sprit Sayls fore and af the Ship aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless in this place, before he quite pass the straights of <hi>Magellanica,</hi> and lose the view of the Horoscope of the <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> of this side the Globe of the world, together with the Horizon, and do enter into the <hi>Oceanus Magnus</hi> of the other side of the terrestrial Globe called the Antipodes, it will behove him to make use of his Geometry, first to know how the living God, the wise <hi>Opifex rerum,</hi> and true work-master of this Terrestrial Globe, hath made the interwoven peece of earth and water, seperated and divided in the orderly way described by <hi>Moses</hi> in the first Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> to hang perpendicular in the Air, even as if a man could by art
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117996:11"/> make a great ball, onion, or apple, or any thing else that is round, to hang in the middle of any spacious room, without touching stay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or supporting of the same: for of a truth the great Terrestrial Globe of earth and sea, even so hangeth in the midle of the aire, and hath nothing to support the pendency thereof, but the Word of the great <hi>Jehova,</hi> witness the Prophet <hi>David</hi> in several of his divine Hymns or heavenly Psalmes, penned by a divine and prophetical spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and that the Antipodes East, is that which we in this side of the Globe do account West, upon the falling of the Sun every day from our Horizon; and that which is their West upon the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Sun every day from their Horizon, upon her assent or ris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Horizon, and elevating of the <hi>Meridian</hi> Horoscope, is our East; so that our <hi>Meridian</hi> Horoscope is their midnight, and their <hi>Meridian</hi> Horoscope is our midnight: neither must the said Navigator understand that in the orderly composure of this Geometrical Globe, the wise <hi>Opifex rerum</hi> hath made it so to exist or be, as our Carpenters or Masons do make their Globe or Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn-work; for then the Navigator aforesaid will be as fearful as many of the passengers and sailers who were in the ship with Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> and Sir <hi>Martin Forbusher,</hi> to pass by, shoot through, or velificate the streights of <hi>Magellanica,</hi> to enter into that unknown Region of the other side of this Terrestial Globe, called the Antipodes.</p>
            <p>But the penman hereof would not have the said Navigator to be ignorant of Astrology, before he attempt the passage of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Region; for it was the unexperiencedness of Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> of this Art, which made him touch with the <hi>Molucco</hi>-Islands in his motion in and to that Horizon, when neither he knew well the location, altitude, or magnitude of the Orion or the Pleiades, spoken of by holy <hi>Job</hi> in his 38 Chapter, and 13 verse of the same; which caused his passage so vagative, tedious, and uncertain: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit our late confectioners of the Celestial and Terrestial Globes have reasonable well illustrated and dimensioned the Stars of the <hi>Coelum stelliferum,</hi> most useful for Navigation and velification on this side of our Horizon, or Globe of the world; yet let the said Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigator take heed of that ignorance that should betray him, or fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardiness that at leastwise should tempt him to pass through the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117996:12"/> straights of <hi>Magellanica,</hi> unless he take heed first to keep a good observation of his <hi>Jacobs</hi>-staffe in the order of the stelliferous lights in that Horizon, which when both Sun and Moon shall faile him, he shall alwayes be sure, as he fell from this part of the Terrestrial Globe, and left our Horizon; so alwayes if he have but a regard of Orion and the Pleiades, albeit he set or departed our Horizon with the Sun, in the South-west and more Westerly parts of the specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative world, as to our understandings in relation to our Terrestrial Globe, yet he shall be sure to rise againe from the Antipodes in the North North-east and more Easterly parts of the universal Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restrial Globe of our Horizon, if he miss of his purpose in the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podes or Merdres of the undal or watry Regions there, if he do not over-shoot the indraught of the gulph of <hi>Persia,</hi> in the North-east longitude and latitude of the inheritance of <hi>Japhet</hi> the second son of the Patriarch <hi>Noah,</hi> which Divine Providence destined and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted unto him and his children for his awful, filial, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest respects to his father, in that he had covered his nakedness in the fit of his fathers drunkenness, well witnessed by <hi>Moses</hi> in the 8 Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and in the 4 verse; and in token of the same, the living God caused the Ark to rest upon the mountaines of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arat,</hi> or <hi>Armenia</hi> the utmost confines thereof, upon the abatement of the waters, after the hundred and fifty dayes increase thereof, to drown the Terrestrial part of the old world, for their grievous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice and violence done one to another, and for want of charity and mercifulness to have been done by one to another: and the same judgement this infant-Commonwealth cannot escape (witness this fearful plague this present Summer) in case the Navigator aforesaid should happen to lose his intended voyage, and not to meet with the Lord Justice, and Lady Mercy, the two Divine Attributes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, and bring them againe into this English Infant-Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and Horizon, to the great Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Westminster,</hi> which lye in 52 degrees Northerly from the elevation of the <hi>Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Horoscope, to do justice on divers persons at this day, in the high places thereof, and so do well; and also to inlarge the poor prisoners of debt, and members of Jesus Christ, to plead the cause of the widow, judge the fatherless, and relieve the oppressed, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessed by the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> in his first Chapter and seventeenth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117996:12"/> verse, to be a sacrifice wonderfully acceptable to the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> the righteous judge of heaven and earth, unto whom the penman hereof would advise the Navigator aforesaid, to humble himself in spirit and truth, and that in the truth and simplicity of the inward man, and not hypocritially, as the Presbyterian gang do at this day in the English Commonwealth; to the end he may be taught the other three Arts and Sciences of Logick, Philosophy, and Arithmetick, before mentioned, together with the use of such Mathematical, and Geometrical instruments, as wilbe needful for the pursuit of the aforesaid intended voyage, for the purposes aforesaid, through the Antipodical Merdres and depths of Neptunes undal surges, and of the unknown Regions of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Saturne,</hi> Celestial and Terrestrial: and being thus furnished, fitted, and accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred (with Gods help) the said Navigator may safely adventure to pass, shoot, and velificate through the streights of <hi>Magellanica,</hi> setting and keeping a direct course to the North-east passage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Meridian Horoscope, or Equinoctial-line of the Antipodes; and to be sure that he faile not to make the Abucca Islands some 12 degrees distant from the Equinoctial-line on that side of the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restrial Globe, where he may come to an Anchor, and make enquiry for his purposes aforesaid: but loosing from hence, and after some few dayes, he must begin to think of passing under the Equinoctial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line in that Horizon, where he must take good heed of an Epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal disease; subject both to himself and sailors, and others the ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company, called the <hi>Episarchia;</hi> And therefore he must be faine to take care to keep himself and them to bodily exercise, and vigilancy, albeit he give them an allowance of two biskets &amp; a full quarter Can to every mess, more then ever he did since hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> passing under, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of our Meridian Horoscope, on our side of the Globe in our Horizon; and to be sure that the next land that they passe by, be the Iranaick Islands, where if they please to touch, they may have most pleasant waters, and varieties, or fruits to refresh their parched and wearied bodies, rosted in their voyage so neer the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Zone</hi> as before hath been declared; where also they may make inquiry for the purposes aforesaid. But if the said Navigator should faile thereof his intended purpose, then must he hie from thence in his course from the Pole Antartique, unto the Pole Artick of that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117996:13"/> Horizon, on that side of the Globe, and be sure that he come faire with the longitude and latitude of the Zaerazans Islands, which lye just under <hi>Prester Johns</hi> territories, and be the certaine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipodes thereunto; and failing also of their purposes there, leaving the Seraphims and purals great Promontory of Sulphurous and bituminous matter, much like the Region of <hi>Terra Delfogo</hi> on curside of the Terrestrial Globe afore mentioned; there will be no help for the Navigator aforesaid, but he must come into the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon of our Terrestial Globe againe, and attempt to adventure through the Indraught of the gulph of <hi>Persia,</hi> and so finde out a ready passage into the <hi>Indian</hi> seas, and to be sure that he do not over-shoot the mouth of the great river Ganges, anciently called Pison, in the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> before spoken of, in the second Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and there to make diligent enquiry for Paradise, and for a place or province that anciently was called there in the old world the land of <hi>Havilah,</hi> that did afford <hi>Solomon</hi> his gold of Ophir, with which he adorned his beautiful temple in Jerusalem, and know of a certaine that there is Bdellium, and the Onix-stone also, and many rich commodities besides, if that were the Navigators Merchandise or errand, for which he must make this long-intended voyage in the ship so built, fitted and prepared as aforesaid, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the aforesaid expert Navigator hath (with Gods providence) certainly made and be come unto the mouth of the aforesaid river, and before that he enter therein for the finding out of the Paradise of God, or Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> out of which man for his sin and disobedience was deservedly expulsed, to the glory of Gods Divine Justice, and to the perpetual shame of rebellious, murderos, and foolishly-traiterous <hi>Adam</hi> our first parent, who did not only wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully rebel and prevaricate against the good and holy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his good and munificent Creator, who had made him Lord of all the works of his creation, well witnessed in the 8 <hi>Psalme</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore spoken of; which commandment expressed in <hi>Genesis,</hi> is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the 17 verse and the second Chapter, and was most holy, good, reasonable and profitable for man, to have kept, and cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and dilligently to have observed, as, if the penman hereof were permitted by the spirit (that he doth write this grand remonstrance to the world) to declare the same, or yet permitted in this place
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117996:13"/> truly to expound and unfold unto the world the true meaning and mystery of the last verse of the third Chapter of <hi>Genesis:</hi> for, to say the truth, what it was that moved our first parents, beside our mother <hi>Eve,</hi> and the evil Angels, to eat the forbidden fruit, the penman hereof may not declare, unless it were such curiosity as the penman hereof to satisfie his curiosity in seeing the <hi>Turkes</hi> Sultanas and Concubines nakedness, for which he had like once to have lost his life at <hi>Conshantinople:</hi> even so unfortunate <hi>Adam,</hi> in his curiosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to see his own and his wives nakedness, did wilfully murder and destroy himself, and his brood, and future posterity; but of a truth, the true sting of this deadly poyson, that hath so contamina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and infected miserable <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his posterity, and that caused <hi>Adams</hi> sin to be so exceedingly sinfully sinful, was not only his disobedience, but his infidelity and ingratitude, in denying of the Justice and Mercy of the living God, who had made him Lord of all the works of his creation, and pre-ordained all the Angels of heaven to be his servants, and to waite upon him; and yet he was such an infidel, as neither to believe Gods word, nor yet gratefully to yeeld obedience thereunto; but in stead thereof, became disconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his Creator, and with the station wherein his wise maker had set him, just as the Angels also were; and so he would be wiser then his Creator had appointed him to be; and therefore since h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Creator had appointed him to be wise in the knowledge only of that which was good, yet he could not rest contented in that good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but he must needs know evil too, which he did atchieve to the knowledge of certainly: but there was never any knowledge or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning since the foundation of the world was laid, purchased at so dear a rate, when for the learning thereof, both the now-divels, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and the woman, <hi>Adams</hi> school-Masters, and himself the apt scholar, and the whole universe his proper dominions, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral creation, were uncosmographied, and blotted out of the book of life; witness Gods final and irrevocable judgement and decree upon them, and pronounced against them in the third Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> the 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, and 19 verses. And lest man should ever presume to come or return to his place againe, contrary to Gods determinate will and decree, whoso reads the last verses of the same Chapter, may easily know what a strong and a strict
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117996:14"/> guard there is kept at the East side of the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> which be no less then Cherubims, and a flaming sword which turneth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way to keep the tree of life.</p>
            <p>And therefore if it should happen that the said Navigator do finde the Garden it self, from which the Navigator must bring these two divine apples of the tree of Life, the Lord Justice, and Lady Mercy; the Penman could well advise him to be wondrous wary how first he begins to move or steer his course upon the <hi>Merdres</hi> of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Seas: for he must expect, at or neer the mouth of the River <hi>Ganges,</hi> to be sorely and often assaulted with several powerful and pestiferous Sea-Monsters, and fishes of prey, yea, even mighty Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathans, and their young whelps, more powerful then any corrupt Parliament, or Counsellor of State, or high Court of Justice-man whatsoever. And mighty and immense Crocodiles, bigger and more fierce and devorative then either corrupt, perjured, trayterous, or factious Committees of Parliament, be they powerful members of the honourable house of Parliament, or greedy sub- or hedge- Committee-men in the several Counties of the English Nation, yea, now or late sitting at Goldsmiths Hall for Sequestrations or Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitions of Delinquents, or else for the fifth and twentieth parts, since the beginning of the Parliament in the English Nation. And Mighty Sharks of an incredible bigness, far bigger then any in the Latitude of <hi>Bermuda</hi> in the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Seas, and more ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinacious (if possible may be) then any Sequestrator whatsoever. mighty Seals, or great Sea-Calfs, far bigger then those are in the <hi>Hebriedes</hi> Islands towards the North seas of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> or any corrupt or exacting Excise-man of the English Nation, who devour both fish and flesh, and whatsoever comes to their jaws. Monstrous Sea-horses, more fierce, velocious, and obnoxious, then either the Traytors <hi>Glyn</hi> or Postmaster <hi>Prideaux</hi> be, or any horse or other beast they keep, or let to hire (themselves onely excepted.) And Grampasses wonderfully enriched with fat, over-grown with swallowing and devouring of the minor fishes of the sea; not much unlike the corrupt Treasurers of Parliament-Committees, sub-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surers of the Navie and Army in <hi>England.</hi> And grand Porpusses, that grunt again with the pinguidity of the rapine of the multitude of those princely fishes called the Herrings, by them daily devoured: not much unlike the Parliament's corrupt Officers of the Custom-house
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117996:14"/> in the English Nation. And swift Dolphins, evermore pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing of the innocent flying fish; which, albeit the wise <hi>Opifex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> hath in his wisdom provided them Vespertilian wings, yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not possibly escape the violent persecutions, or nimble rapes of their enemies the Dolphins; well to be compared to those corrupt Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Serjeants at Arms-men Pursuivants, and other their Pieddees, and Villains in Buckram, and Wagstaves of the English Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and Nation, all under pretence of Supreme Authority. Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with those devouring Pikes higher up in the River, sometimes in fresh waters, &amp; somtimes in salt waters, that prey at no aim; not much unlike those, <hi>Martins, Dallisons Coxes, Phelps, Kirks,</hi> and many more of their fellows, Committees Clerks of the English Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. And together also with those two pure Remora's, well <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belized</hi> and <hi>Frostified,</hi> with one <hi>John Roseforth</hi> Yeoman, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself <hi>Rushworth,</hi> now a learned Gentleman of the Long Robe; and one Goodman <hi>Bishop</hi>'s son, late Goodman <hi>Bradshaw</hi>'s son of <hi>Cheshier</hi>'s man: who, if the Navigator be not very wary, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l stop the course of his velification up the River <hi>Ganges,</hi> if they can but get between the Rudder and the lower Keel of the ship a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid, and be but acquainted with the Navigators Message or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand to bring back the Lord Justice and Lady Mercy again into the English Commonwealth; and if the danger of the <hi>Indian</hi> Rajeras which be petty Kings in the great Moguls territories, and live only upon robberies, be well considered, together also with the natural fierceness of the wild, rapinous, and indomable beasts of prey, besides many venomous and pestilent beasts ingendring and naturally breathing in the <hi>Indian</hi> Horizon, on land, much about the <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culean</hi> Pillars, which never yet could be passed by any, and that any history maketh mention of, save <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, who in that age of the world did conquer <hi>Porus</hi> the great Mogul or Emperor, or chief King of <hi>India,</hi> who made a voyage on purpose upon the bancks of the river of <hi>Ganges</hi> by land, and did with much difficulty and loss of many of his old <hi>Macedenian</hi> and <hi>Grecian</hi> souldiers, march up the river <hi>Ganges,</hi> as high as <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars, and about two dayes journy above: but being a heathen Prince, and assaulted with divers evil spirits, who keep their residence in those parts, a little below the very local Paradise, or Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117996:15"/> described by <hi>Moses</hi> as aforesaid, who were afraid lest he should come neer Ophir, so called by the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> or the penman of the first book of <hi>Kings,</hi> and second book of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> and rob those hell-hounds of the gold, Bdellium, and Onix-stones, and other the riches of these parts; for the lucre thereof, unjustly to be given to several of the simple inhabitants in those parts of the world, and divers others, they daily bewitch the lost sons of <hi>Adam</hi> to make contracts with them, to serve them idolatrously, and to forsake the worship of the ever-living God, the holy one of <hi>Israel:</hi> for of a truth the penman hereof is bold to remonstrate unto the world, that the devil is so good a fortune-teller, that he could easily tell that <hi>Alexander</hi> the great being a heathen Prince, should not come neer the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> or local Paradise, from whence both miserable man himself, and his brood, and the serpent into which he entered, were cast out upon the fall of man: nevertheless <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, at the end of two dayes journey or march with his Army, after he had also set up a statue of the Image of <hi>Mars</hi> in remembrance of his many victories, and had sacrificed thereunto, he returned down againe upon the banks of the river of <hi>Ganges;</hi> and his great horse <hi>Bucephalus</hi> happening there to dye, he most superstitiously did intombe him, and built a famous City in remembrance of his horse, and called the name thereof <hi>Buce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia;</hi> but whether it bear the same name to this day, the penman hereof cannot perfectly remonstrate to the world; only as it appears by <hi>Hannibal Roselli</hi> the <hi>Italian,</hi> and divers other Authors which the penman hath seen in <hi>France, Germany, Italy, Rome, Madrill,</hi> and at <hi>Venice,</hi> and some at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> both in the Greek, and Latine Tongues, and some in <hi>Syriack, Chaldean, Persian,</hi> and <hi>Phenician</hi> Languages (in which the penman hereof had some skill in those dayes) it appeared to the penman hereof, that his march upon the river <hi>Ganges,</hi> and his conquest made over wilde beasts and venemous beasts, and his labour and travel therein, was more toilesome, and laborious unto him, then all the territories he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered: for there he met with and was encountred with a wild and fierce beast, called an <hi>Odons,</hi> which slew above 60 of his <hi>Numidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> horsemen, and his old Commilitones, as my Author called them: his colour is black, his bigness is as great and like to a Bull: he hath
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117996:15"/> two strait horns in his front like Unicorns, mouthed like a Wolf; fore-parted and pawed like unto a Lion, his hinde-parts like unto a stoned-horse, or hind-parts of a Bull, and his skin is very hard, and impenetrable with any Lance: well compared to some corrupt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-men, now or late of the English Nation. And also with Troops of Elephants; but these he defeated with the grunning of swine whipt, which his School-master <hi>Seneca</hi> had taught him to do (brought in Tumbrels for that purpose) well compared to bugbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sir <hi>John Presbyter</hi> with his simple Synod, and out-cowed Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of <hi>London,</hi> countenanced underhand evermore by the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and worst part of the corrupt Parliament-men of <hi>England.</hi> And also with several fell Dragons, well compared to the traiterous <hi>Prideaux</hi> and his complices, corrupt members of the high Court of Justice, who laboured divers members sitting in that honorable assembly, to break the faith of the Lord General and Army given at <hi>Exeter</hi> to Sir <hi>John Stowel,</hi> and others, upon the rendition of the town, on purpose to bring a curse from heaven upon them, and so to destroy them; much like the counsels of <hi>Baalam,</hi> which caused the trespass to be committed by <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> and divers other of the people of the Lord, for which 24000 of them fell by the plague, as appears by the 25 of <hi>Numbers,</hi> and at the 9 verse: but let the traytors take heed they do not provoke the holy one of <hi>Israel</hi> too much, for fear lest it befall them as afterwards it befell the Southsayer <hi>Baalam,</hi> who would entrap the Lords people, as the traitor <hi>Prideaux, Glinne,</hi> and their complices, have conspired to do these many yeers against the Lords Army, which example is left by <hi>Moses,</hi> recorded to all future ages in the 31 Chapter of <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> aforesaid, and at the 8 verse. And also in many places, where he came too neer the river side; he was assaulted by several Wyverns, much-like unto <hi>Griffins,</hi> and very fierce and venemous, well compar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a corrupt councel of States-man, who is wel known to the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yet his name shall be here concealed; but if he repent not sooner, he and the old Vulpones, Sodomitical, and treacherous favorite, may both fortune to be hanged at White-hall-gate, for doing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice, and ride the same horse that <hi>Trecillian, Bambre,</hi> and <hi>Baugh</hi> the then Kings Attourny did in <hi>Richard</hi> the seconds time, if the Lord Justice and the Lady Mercy can be brought from Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dise
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117996:16"/> by the said Navigator; the one of them with his Buckram-bag, and the other with the Jewels which lately proceeded out of the late Tyrant his Masters Coffers, about their necks; and one goodman <hi>Cooks</hi> son in <hi>Essex</hi> also for company. And he was assaulted also with several Tygres, well compared to corrupt Judges in <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi>-hall, whose colours well resemble their bloody tyrannous scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let robes. And also with several fierce Panthers, much like the traitor <hi>Prideaux,</hi> who albeit he stands charged with high treason, yet both Wolf-like, and Panther-like, he still continues his rapines amongst the Lambes of this Commonwealth, and all for want of the Lord Justice, and the Lady Mercy. And also with several Anthelopes, well compared to all corrupt Maiors of Corporations, assisted ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more with a corrupt Recorder of the same, being alwayes a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the long robe, a perfect Wolf of the English Nation; and they be one to another evermore, as the fierce Lions of <hi>Africa,</hi> and their Jackalles, be one to another: or else they be assisted with some fierce Bear or Bears-whelpe of this Nation, being called a Serjeant at Law. And also divers immense Foxes of a greater magnitude then any Country breeds, and Man-keen, well compared to corrupt Prothonotaries and Registers of divers Courts of Justice in the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Commonwealth, both Ecclesiastical, legal and civil. And also with Badyers, Pates, or Grayes, of a Lupunary instinct and nature; with several little Badgerets, well compared to corrupt Jeffery kindle-cole-ing Attornyes Clerks, Sollicitors, and other their imps, proper and apt to stir up and raise contentions, Law-suits, troubles, and vexations, betwixt neighbour and neighbour; clean contrary to the directions of that most famous Doctor of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who expresly forbids the same, in the 6 Chapter of his Epistle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> from the first to the 13 verse. And for vermine, such as Hedge-hogs, Pole-cats, or great Wood-cats; wilde and savage, but very fierce Wesels, Ferrets, Rats and Mice, fitly compared to Burn-bayliffs, Serjeants at Mace, Marshals-men, and Catch-poles, both for the innumerableness and mischievous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of them. Besides also, he was assaulted with divers fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and great Cerustaes, Sloworms, gliding Serpents, and Toads, and mighty Locusts, very noisome, venomous and pestilent; fitly to be compared to Sir <hi>John Presbyter,</hi> his Priests, and all his gang or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117996:16"/> Hierarchy of unclean spirits, who daily sting, bite, and poison, and invenome all people passing by that way. Neither can the penman hereof possibly express these several kinds, nor yet the multitude of Hornets, Wasps, and immense Drone-bees, Gnats, Muskeets, and other sorts of pestiferous, noisome, and troublesome Flyes, wherewith this poor Prince <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, and his soldiers, and their Horses, were tormented, vexed, stung, bitten and disquieted; not unaptly compared to busie Constables, Headburroughs, and their Beadles in <hi>London,</hi> Marshals-men, together with exacting and prowling petty Judges and Officers in many Courts of Justice, in the English Commonwealth, such as be Box-keepers, Bag-bearers, Cryers, Tipstaves, Vergers, the corrupt Judges Foot-cloth-men, with their Clerks of Petitions, Bayles, Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zances, Fines, and such like, together with the Warden of the Fleets well-rivetted Deputy (anciently one of the subtillest knaves in <hi>England</hi>) and his men, Wardens, Waiters, Turn-keys, Cellar-keepers, and Chamber-sweepers; together with the Just-asses of the Peace, well Longing, far Lowder, better Elveshead, and Pywater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toned, and Sabbatarianized, with their Clerks, never out of league with a crue of Bawdes, Whores, Pimpes, Panders, Sharkes, and Crowders, alwayes assisted with perjured, Calcatted, and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous under-Sheriffs, their Deputies and Clerks; besides general Clerks of the peace, and Clerks of the Assizes, evermore-attended with their Goalers, Prison-keepers, or their Deputies; together also with their infernal Officers, as under-keepers, Turn-Keyes, Book-keepers, Clerks of Prisons, Waiters, Vulcanists, or Yeomen of the Bolt or Hand-cuff, Tormenters, <hi>Dericks</hi> Yeomen of the Halter, and Hang-men, the very pest and vermin of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Nation. And therefore the penman hereof considering all these enemies seriously, that the Navigator must inevitably encounter withal, when he hath sayled above <hi>Hercules</hi> pillars, or <hi>Alexanders</hi> statue, where the river <hi>Ganges</hi> (which springs in the Garden of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi>) beginneth to grow unnavigable, then upon necessity he must be compelled to march at least ten dayes journy through the land an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently called <hi>Havilah</hi> in <hi>Moses</hi> time, and <hi>Ophir</hi> in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, where upon his entrance thereof, he must expect day and night to be grievously assaulted with evil Angels and soule spirits of mighty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117996:17"/> power, subtility and pestilency, a touch whereof Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth give unto the <hi>Ephesians</hi> in the 6 Chapter and 11 verse, and most elegantly doth describe these spiritual monsters, whose chief resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the world be in those parts, out of their envy to mankinde, both before their and his fall, and since; when he cals them principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, powers, rulers of darkness in this world, and spiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses in high places; and especially when they understand that man is to enter into Paradise again, to fetch the two golden apples of Justice and Mercy from the tree of Life.</p>
            <p>And also that the said Navigator shall also let him know, that he hath a Commission under King Jesus, from the General and Saints of the English Nation and Armies (who be the Lambs bride) to bring from thence not onely the apples and fruit of the tree of life, but also some of the leaves thereof, to heal the Nations of the world, whom their Masters <hi>Lucifer, Beelzebub,</hi> and <hi>Tartan,</hi> have so long and grievously wounded. But above all, it is not to be expressed with what malicious raging, and hideous assaults, and fiery torments, with thunderings, lightnings, and earthquakes (as if the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth were upon a present dissolution, and returning to their first Chaos) the said Navigator will be assaulted withal, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frightened, amazed, amused, and astonished, when the Navigator having the Book of Life in his hand, and shall read but the three first verses of the twentieth Chapter of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> in those evil spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits hearing.</p>
            <p>And note, that he will make the Navigator, if he be not a perfect Christian, to retreat, and to proceed no further in his intended Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towards Paradise, albeit he be never so neer it, and have passed so far on his voyage, and with such difficulties as before is rehearsed. And if none of these furious affrights can deter the Navigator afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said from his intended Voyage, then all the gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> being at hand, <hi>Bdellium</hi> and <hi>Onix</hi>-stones, together with all the riches of <hi>India,</hi> shall be proferred by those subtil and evil spirits, unto the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigator aforesaid, to perswade him to stay his voyage to Paradise: but the Navigator must beware that he be not corrupted or tempted by those evil spirits: but the Navigator's answer must be the same that his Saviour's was, upon the same occasion, and well witnessed and recorded to future ages of eternity, in the 4 Chapter of Saint
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117996:17"/>
               <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Gospel, and the 10 verse.</p>
            <p>And let the Navigator be sure that he moare the ship well before he come to an Anchor, for fear of violent storms raised in those parts, by those evil spirits: and be sure also that they have regard of their provisions of victuals; for those evil spirits are very subtil and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thieves, and will be apt to steal, or any wise destroy the bread and bisket of the ships provisions (knowing that God hath made bread the staff of mans life) on purpose to destroy mankinde, or drive him to despair for hunger, or otherwise to tempt him as the devil did, when he kept our blessed Saviour, and now crucified and glorified King Jesus, fourty days and fourty nights, until he was an hungry; and then he came upon him subtilly with several temptations (think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have tempted him) but he was deceived, as by Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> it is recorded to all eternity in his Gospel, in several places of the fourth Chapter thereof; and with many more temptations, try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, fightings and combatings, too many for the penman hereof to express.</p>
            <p>And the penman hereof doth further remonstrate, that after the Navigator hath passed the borders of <hi>Havilah</hi> or <hi>Ophir,</hi> he must expect to ascend several high mountaines, before he can come to the East parts of the garden, which be guarded with Cherubims and a flaming sword; and of a truth, the said river <hi>Ganges,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds out of Paradise, whose ascent is very high, descends lower up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the fall thereof, then <hi>Nilus</hi> doth from the <hi>Lunae montes,</hi> or James river in <hi>Virginia</hi> doth descend from the fals above the City of James-Town, so called in those parts, or any water if poured down from the top or uttermost ascent of the mountaines of <hi>Ararat</hi> in <hi>Armenia,</hi> neer unto the place where <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, and the famous <hi>Darius,</hi> the last <hi>Median</hi> and <hi>Persian</hi> great Monarch, joyned battel; which is by learned men, and many ancient writers, held both to be the place where <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark rested after the deluge, as before hath been remonstrated; as also to be the highest inland mountaine or ascent in the world, but especially in <hi>Asia</hi> Major, where the penman hereof is confident the garden of <hi>Eden</hi> was, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly described by <hi>Moses</hi> in the second Chapter of <hi>Genesis,</hi> as before hath been sufficiently evidenced.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117996:18"/>
            <p>And therefore the penman hereof doth further remonstrate unto the world, that since this voyage wil prove so tedious, so troublesome, so hazardous, and so jeopardous unto the Navigator, and so fatal to the divel and his Angels, and to all wicked men, and so full of utility and benefit to the present Commonwealth and Armies of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Nation, and so full of joy and earthly comfort and consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to every free-born person of the same, in this present Life, and future happiness and eternal beatitude in the world to come, It will be necessary for the Navigator aforesaid, to have a good guard of his person assigned him by the noble General and Officers of the present Armies of the English Nation, to guard his person and ship from Sea-pyrats, aswel in his velifications by sea, as in his several marches by land, as often as this expert Navigator shal have occasion to cast Anchor, and move by land any way in order of the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this voyage: which must consist only of three full Foot-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, every company numbred and allowed to be thereto 120 old souldiers, but the best and newest refined Saints of the whole three Armles in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> such as only have read, understood, or practised the counsel of Saint <hi>John Baptist,</hi> which he gave unto the <hi>Romane</hi> souldiers in the 3 Chapter of Saint <hi>Lukes</hi> Gospel, expressed in the 14 verse thereof, when they came al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to him to be baptized of him in <hi>Jordan;</hi> and be men of sound constitutions of body, ingenious mindes, and healthy complexions, manly, valiant, prudent, and patient of labor and travel; and be very willing to go the voyage intended (by Gods providence, thus marshalled and disciplinated under their three Captaines, whose names must be Fidele Prudence, Sperant Fortitude, Charitable Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy, with each of them his Lieutenant and Ensign, assisted with three Serjeants, four Corporals, and two compleat Drums, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trophies belonging to military discipline. And they being thus ordered for conduct, there will remaine 108 souldiers, which being divided into three divisions, will make eighteen Files, that is six Files of Musketteers upon the right divison, and six upon the left di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision; and the other six Files of Pikes placed in the middle division: and these will be alwayes fit, thus marshalled and marched, for any service, be it to guard the said Navigator upon all his landings, in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117996:18"/> point of exploration, or otherwise upon his advance by land from the side of the great river <hi>Ganges</hi> upon the <hi>Indian</hi> soile, against the fury of the wilde beasts aforesaid, being either ravenous, pestilent, or venemous. And they must also testifie to the Lord Justice, and the Lady Mercy, that the new Engagement or national Covenant of the English Commonwealth and Armies, hath been solemnly taken by every member of the English Nation. And the Navigator afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said is to take good heed that this ship be very well victualled, and Ammunitioned, both with Basilisquoes, Canons, Demicanons, Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, Demy-Culvering, Mignian and Saker, together with two, if not four small Drakes, Chambers or Morter-peeces, upon the upper Decks of the said ship; together with good store of ship-Muskets, and Callivers; together with wast-bands for the same; pendants and streamers, and in all postures fit for a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of War: and for horse, there will be little or no need for them, but that neer unto the aforesaid place before recited, where <hi>Alexander</hi> the great was assaulted with the evil spirits, the Navigator must be sure also, if he finde not the Lord Justice and Lady Mercy, in some other places of his voyage, undoubtedly he must be faine, yea forced to pass through, maugre all opposition whatsoever; therefore it will be necessary, that, before he undertake the said voyage, there be a general day of humiliation kept (unto the living God) for a blessing upon the Navigator in the undertakings aforesaid, by the Saints of the English Armies and Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>After which, the solemn Engagement formerly prescribed to be taken by the people of the Armies, is to be read again, and confirmed by the people and souldiers of the Army, and again solemnly subscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by the people and Armies, with a cordial protestation, and a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral exclamation; that as the cursed Jews upon the crucifying of Christ, in the 19 Chapter and 15 verse of Saint <hi>Johns</hi> Gospel, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed king Jesus their true and undoubted King before <hi>Pilate</hi> and the whole world, and affirmed that they had no king but <hi>Cesar;</hi> so the English people and the souldiery of the Armies thereof, have not, nor will for ever hereafter have any king but Christ; and that a Duplicate of this Engagement, Protestation, and general acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the People and Armies, be sent forthwith to be inrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117996:19"/> upon the records of this Commonwealth; as also with the Judge-Advocate general of the Armies; and that the original of this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, Protestation, and general acknowledgement, may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to the Navigator aforesaid, to the end that in this long voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age he may never want a winde.</p>
            <p>Being thus fitted, he shall be evermore assured to have the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the holy Ghost to fill the Sails of the said Ship, after they be hoisted, and the Anchors levated: so that in very short time, with Gods gracious assistance, which he may be as well assured of, as that the Penman hereof is the author hereof, and had not at the time of the penning hereof, any other help of humane learning then the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor yet so much as a Map, or Terrestrial Globe, or Celestial Globe, to pen to the Navigator the description of this voyage afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, which the Penman hereof will hazard his life that the Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor will perform in a very short time, if he be fitted and accoutred as is hereby advised and declared.</p>
            <p>The onely difficulty will be, that when the Navigator comes to Anchor neer to the head of <hi>Ganges,</hi> and can sail no further, but must be forced to come to Anchor upon the banks of the River, and to travel by Land above <hi>Hercules</hi> pillars, and <hi>Alexander</hi>'s statue aforesaid, to Paradise, That then he fit the three Foot-Companies marshalled as aforesaid, with all convenient Armour Military, and usual Arms of Muskets, Fire-locks, Pocket-pistols, and Pikes, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so with good store of Powder and Shot, Fire-balls, and casting Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throps, to annoy the feet of the wilde, pestilent, and ravenous beasts aforesaid; likewise, Bowes, and good store of barbed Arrows inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed, to destroy those violent Mankeen, and pestilent beasts that they must expect inevitably to encounter with, upon their landing, after they be come to an Anchor.</p>
            <p>And as the said Navigator must take great care that he thus arm, prepare, and marshal three Foot-Companies of the Saints of the English Armies temporally; so he must also arm them spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, for the combating with, fighting, and counter-assaulting of the evil spirits wherewith they shall without all doubt be grievously vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they come neer the confines of <hi>Havilah</hi> and <hi>Ophir,</hi> as hath been sufficiently remonstrated to the whole world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117996:19"/> the Penman hereof doth seriously advise the Navigator, before he comes neer, or attempts to pass by or thorow any of those parts so possessed, guarded, and inhabited with evil spirits, That he and his whole company do cordially humble themselves in spirit to God the Father; the onely Father of all spirits, with the New Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and English Protestation spread before him, according to the example of good King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and let the Navigator pray to the Lord of hosts, that, for the Lord King Jesus Christ his sake, he will command three Companies of the Saints triumphant, under their Captain-General King Jesus, who is also already mounted upon his white horse, and gone forth conquering and to conquer, as before hath been d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>clared; to every Company consisting also of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty Patriarchs, Prophets, Apostles, Martyrs, Saints, and spirits of godly men depared, marshalled and disciplinated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Celestial Military discipline, under <hi>Michael, Raphael,</hi> and <hi>Adriel,</hi> three of the Arch-angels of the living God, and old combatants with <hi>Lucifer, Beelzebub,</hi> and <hi>Tartan,</hi> the three of the first great orders of Angels called Seraphims; of that immense power in celestial places, that, most Dragon-like, with their tails they drew the third part of the stars of heaven with them, upon their first combat that happened betwixt <hi>Michael</hi> and his angels, and the devil and his angels, as holy Writ sufficiently testifies.</p>
            <p>And then, besides the Navigator and his Militant Souldiers out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and temporal armour, he must be sure that before yet they must adventure to pass by, thorow, or come neer the confines of <hi>Havilah</hi> or <hi>Ophir,</hi> to come neer or approach the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> he and his three Foot-Companies must put on the girdle of Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, brestplate of righteousness, shooes of the preparation of the Gospel of peace, shield of faith, helmet of salvation, and sword of the Spirit, being all the armour of God, expressed by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the sixth Chapter of his Epistle to the <hi>Ephesians,</hi> and from the 10 to the 19 verse of the same.</p>
            <p>And the Penman hereof doth further advise and admonish the Navigator aforesaid, that missing of his purpose in all the parts of the world, and being necessitated to enter into the Paradise of God for the divine Attributes aforesaid, called [the Lord Justice and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117996:20"/> Mercy] being thus perfectly and compleatly fitted and accoutred souldier-like, armed <hi>cap a pied,</hi> and wanting nothing that might stay, hinder, or resist his voyage to the further end, save a Herald at Arms, to declare (to the Cherubims and guards of the flaming sword turning every way, which keep the way of the tree of life, figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively growing in paradise) the message of the Navigator afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, and to let them know the Commission he hath to enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, notwithstanding their Commissions be as ancient and vetust as the fall of Man, to keep man out. And therefore the Penman hereof doth seriously advise the Navigator aforesaid, again (when he hath approached within the view thereof) to humble himself and his company to the Father of all spirits, and in the Name of King Jesus, and incessantly and urgently to beseech him to send that old and true princely Ambassadour of good tidings and Evangelical truth, <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Archangel, who brought the news first into the world of the birth of <hi>John</hi> the Baptist, and Jesus Christ the Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel of righteousness, witness Saint <hi>Luke</hi> in his first Chapter, at the 13 and 31 verses of the same: who being come, and having deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the Navigator's message, then shall the Navigator be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with admitted into the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> and be shewed all the trees, herbs, and plants growing in the garden, which were appointed by God for man to eat, as also the tree of knowledge of good and evil. Then will the Navigator be driven to explore, try, and search out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst all the trees of Paradise, for the tree of life.</p>
            <p>But if he chance to have the Book of life, and look well into the last Chapter of the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Saint <hi>John,</hi> and into the second verse of the same, he will, with the perusal of the 25 <hi>Psalm</hi> of the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> and well expounding of the 8, 9, and 10 verses of the same, easily finde and perceive which is the tree of life, from which he must pull the two golden apples of Justice and Mercy. And let him be sure, that, according to the number of the Nations expressed in the great Map of the world, being contained in <hi>Europa, Asia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> he bring along with him so many leaves of the tree of life, which will be very convenient for the use and application of the General and Saints of the English Armies in all places of the world where they shall set their foot, and happen
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117996:20"/> to subdue and conquer with their sword, under their Captain-General King Jesus: after the Nations have been wounded, smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and subdued with the sword, those leaves shall and will, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly applied, heal so many of the people thereof, as the holy One of <hi>Israel</hi> hath appointed to Salvation, by conversion of them to faith in Christ, and observing of Christs new commandment that he gave to his disciples, witnessed in Sain <hi>Johns</hi> Gospel at the 12 verse and in the 15 Chapter.</p>
            <p>And when thus the Navigator hath atchieved the sum and end of his voyage, after solemne exultation of spirit to the Father of all spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, and cordial thankfulness, and serious Protestation, with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned purpose to hold the new national English Covenant and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement made by the General Saints, of the Army, and the English Commonwealth, by the Navigator, and his three Companies of the souldiery aforesaid with him, on their own and English Armies and Commonwealths behalf; and a short repetition of the Lords prayer from the bowels of their soules, and a short supplication for Gods protection, for Christ his sake, in their return, Then it will be necessary they return for <hi>England</hi> with all speed; and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, tread the same footsteps, by which they came; first descending of the exceeding high mountaine, upon which they came to the garden of <hi>Eden;</hi> and it is an exceeding high mountain, and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther save that which is mentioned in the fourth Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthews</hi> Gospel, and at the 8 verse; into which our blessed Saviour was taken by the tempter, when he shewed unto him all the kingdoms of the world and the glory thereof, and proferred to give the same unto Christ, if by any means he could have perswaded Christ to have committed idolatry: &amp; therefore the land of <hi>Havilah</hi> and <hi>Ophir</hi> being so neer thereunto, it is no marvel but the Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator and his company must be careful upon their return, of the silver, the wedge of gold, and Babylonish garment, stoln, taken, and hid by <hi>Achan,</hi> expressed in the 7 of <hi>Joshua</hi> and the 21 verse, and forbear to meddle with any treasure, or other things in the devils territories, but soberly and civilly return to the ship at Anchor in the said river of <hi>Ganges;</hi> and having shipped his men, and hoisted up his sailes, let him saile and velificate down to the mouth of the river back
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117996:21"/> into the <hi>Indian</hi> sea, and direct his course due South, leaving <hi>India</hi> on the startboard-hand, and untill he make the famous and fertil Islands of <hi>Japan</hi> commended by all travellers to be the delightfullest place in the habitable world, which possible might be the cause that moved the great Atheist Sir <hi>Matthew de Renze,</hi> about 15 or 16 yeers ago, dying in <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon making his Will, and ordaining another Atheist like himself named Sir <hi>Henry Peirce,</hi> sometimes Secretary to the Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> sometimes Deputy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and one Master <hi>Monke</hi> of the Custome-house, his Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and willed that after twenty or thirty dayes, there should be a ship built, bought, or hired at <hi>Waterford</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to take in his soul there, and to make a voyage on purpose to carry his soul to the Islands of <hi>Japan,</hi> but not to land or come to an Anchor, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn within view thereof; which was accordingly done and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Executors, as the penman hereof hath credibly heard, when he lived in <hi>Ireland:</hi> but mark the sequel; for albeit the ship and sailors that undertook this voyage, had a quick and nimble pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage thither from <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet in the view of the Islands, was the ship, and men and all, at noon-day, in faire calme weather, by a whirle-winde, occasioned by a <hi>Corpes pesant,</hi> so tearmed by Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ingurgitated and swallowed up into the Ocean, and never seen more: a fearful example for all Atheists to take warning by. And when the late tyrannical Deputy heard tell thereof, he sent for Sir <hi>Matthew de Renzies</hi> son, now or late alive in <hi>London,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned him in the Castle of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and hooked a good end of his wealth, which his father had left to him at his death, for making of such an Athestical Will, and some other crimes supposed to be done by his son or father in his life time.</p>
            <p>And from these Islands of <hi>Japan,</hi> if the Navigator steer and direct his course South-west and by West, with Gods providence in short time he will come into the latitude of <hi>Madagaskar,</hi> and from thence to the Cape <hi>de bono speranzo;</hi> and having doubled the Cape, and left the <hi>Affrican</hi> shore on the startboard-hand, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of his course due North, he will acquire the latitude of the <hi>Azores</hi> Islands, about 400 miles from the lands end of <hi>England,</hi> and so strait up the narrow seas due West, untill he come to the Isle
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117996:21"/> of <hi>Wight;</hi> and so going through the Needles, &amp; leaving the Isle upon the startboard-hand, he may saile up to <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> where will be most convenient for him to land his men; who may declare to their fellow-souldiers the wonderful difficulties that they and their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigator have gone through, suffered, and endured, for the perfecting of the voyage aforesaid; and desire them solemnly to joyn in thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving with them for their safe return and deliverances from so many eminent dangers as they have gone through in the voyage aforesaid; but above all, for Gods infinite love, mercy, and kindeness unto them in Jesus Christ, their heavenly King, who had vouchsafed to bring them safe into paradise, and to permit them to pull the two golden apples of Justice and Mercy, and abundance of the leaves also from the tree of life, to be brought into this Nation once more, to be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here in this infant-Commonwealth of free-born English men, and poor humbled Saints militant of the Armies in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this being done, present news hereof may be forthwith sent to the Noble General and the whole Armies, and to every free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born person of the English Commonwealth, who desire to see, and be cordially acquainted with the two Divine Attributes of Almighty God, the Lord Justice and the Lady Mercy: and that there may not only be a speedy preparation made for the entertainment of them, when the Navigator aforesaid hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken the voyage aforesaid, in the said ship, in such manner as the penman hath hereof chalked him out the way, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his voyage, and brought them accordingly; but a grand, cordial, and unanimous inthronizing of them in the hearts of every faithfull Christian man of the English Commonwealth; so as we may be ready all of us to meet King Jesus, the sweet bridegrome of our souls, when he cometh to marry this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Commonwealth to himself, which will be either in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Mercy, before <hi>Midsummer</hi>-day next, one thousand six hundred fifty two, albeit the fool hath said in his heart, there is no God; and therefore those fools be totally corrupt, and have done abominable iniquity; there is none doth good: and as it was said in the days of the Prophet <hi>David</hi> in the Commonwealth of <hi>Israel,</hi> just so it is now in the English Commonwealth; and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117996:22"/> therefore well did he speak the words before rehearsed, and complaine to the living God, being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mplete with Divine sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for the iniquity of that age in <hi>Israel,</hi> as appears by his 53 <hi>Psalme</hi> and the first verse; but if the Prophet were alive againe in the English Nation, he would complaine to some purpose.</p>
            <p>And therefore the penman hereof, whilest the ship is at sea, will daily pray for her safe return, and alwayes rest,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A servant to his Excellency, Army and Commonwealth, whilst he is a member of Jesus Christ in the flesh, or of this present Commonwealth, or is alive to be <hi>Tho. Elslyot</hi> Ar. Ar. Conq.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117996:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>